<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Data Analysis with R</title><link href="http://benoitdherin.github.io/data-analysis-with-R/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://benoitdherin.github.io/data-analysis-with-R/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://benoitdherin.github.io/data-analysis-with-R/</id><updated>2014-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Problem Dimensions</title><link href="http://benoitdherin.github.io/data-analysis-with-R/Dimensions.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Benoit Dherin</name></author><id>tag:benoitdherin.github.io,2014-03-04:data-analysis-with-R/Dimensions.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In broad sense, &lt;strong&gt;Data Analysis&lt;/strong&gt; is a &lt;strong&gt;collection of methods&lt;/strong&gt; allowing us to &lt;strong&gt;answer questions&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;solve problems&lt;/strong&gt; in any given field using &lt;strong&gt;data&lt;/strong&gt; relevant to the questions or problems. Usually, going from the data to the answer of your problem involves a &lt;strong&gt;process&lt;/strong&gt; or workflow that can be describes as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;problem statement&lt;/strong&gt;: state the problem, identify the ideal data set relevant to that problem, along with the appropriate type of analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;data collection:&lt;/strong&gt; collect (possibly various sources) as much as possible of the data (possibly in various formats) that will allow you to build the best approximation of your ideal data set.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;data preparation:&lt;/strong&gt; construct the ideal data set from your collected data; this involves cleaning the data (dealing with aberrant or missing values), selecting an appropriate subset of the collected data, putting the data in a &lt;strong&gt;regular form&lt;/strong&gt; (i.e. multidimensional arrays of values)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;data analysis:&lt;/strong&gt; perform the appropriate analysis on the regularized data, and see if you can answer your initial problem on the ground of this analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;data visualization:&lt;/strong&gt; try to convey the result of your data analysis using an expressive visualization, accessible to laymen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As stated the first step of a data analysis, beside setting up your problem is to determine the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ideal data set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;appropriate analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to answer your question. To be able to do that, you need to determine the dimensions invoved in your problem. There are essentially three dimensions to a data analysis questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;population dimension&lt;/strong&gt;: Typically, your problem involves a set of objects (individual, entities, etc.), which one calls the &lt;strong&gt;population&lt;/strong&gt;. For instance, you may be interested finance questions, in which case your population will most probably be a collection of stocks. The population is usually denoted by &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(\Omega\)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;variable dimension&lt;/strong&gt;: Along with a population of object under study your problem most probably involved a collections of characteristics, called &lt;strong&gt;variables&lt;/strong&gt; associated to each object in your population. In the case of portfolio question, these may be the closing price, the transaction volume for these stocks, the number of employees of the corresponding company, etc. given stock,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;temporal dimension&lt;/strong&gt;: At last, any observation of a characteristic or variable for a given individual has a time stamp. For most situations, one can imagine having data points taken at regular intervals in a time window. For instance, in a population of stocks, the closing price, transaction volume, and employee number can be collected on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These three dimensions are faily broad and most problems can be decomposed as a problem involving one or tow of these dimensions. Questions involving the whole three dimension are of course the hardest, necessiting the full spectrum of data analysis method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very general representation of &lt;strong&gt;regular data&lt;/strong&gt; corresponding to a problem involving the three dimensions is a 3 dimensional cube of numbers as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html"&gt;
&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://pythonhosted.org/cubes/_images/cube-dims_and_cell.png" alt="dataCube" /&gt;&lt;p class="caption"&gt;dataCube&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>The Variable Dimension</title><link href="http://benoitdherin.github.io/data-analysis-with-R/Variables.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Benoit Dherin</name></author><id>tag:benoitdherin.github.io,2014-03-04:data-analysis-with-R/Variables.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>The Population Dimension</title><link href="http://benoitdherin.github.io/data-analysis-with-R/Population.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Benoit Dherin</name></author><id>tag:benoitdherin.github.io,2014-03-03:data-analysis-with-R/Population.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>The Time Dimension</title><link href="http://benoitdherin.github.io/data-analysis-with-R/Time.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Benoit Dherin</name></author><id>tag:benoitdherin.github.io,2014-03-02:data-analysis-with-R/Time.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Data Collection</title><link href="http://benoitdherin.github.io/data-analysis-with-R/Collection.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-26T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Benoit Dherin</name></author><id>tag:benoitdherin.github.io,2014-02-26:data-analysis-with-R/Collection.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Data Preparation</title><link href="http://benoitdherin.github.io/data-analysis-with-R/Preparation.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-02-24T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Benoit Dherin</name></author><id>tag:benoitdherin.github.io,2014-02-24:data-analysis-with-R/Preparation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>